<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of usury further debated, in a letter to the author of usury stated.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 90 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31198</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1192</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213538</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825896</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825896</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30287</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31198)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30287)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 1774:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of usury further debated, in a letter to the author of usury stated.</title>
                  <author>T. P.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.D. for Jonathan Robinson at the Golden Lion in S.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Possibly a reply to: T.P.  Usury stated being a reply to Mr. Jelinger's Usurer cast.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>T. P. --  Usury stated being a reply to Mr. Jelinger's Usurer cast.</term>
               <term>Jelinger, Christopher. --  Usurer cast.</term>
               <term>Usury stated being a reply to Mr. Jelinger's Usurer cast.</term>
               <term>Usurer cast.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30287:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CASE OF USURY Further Debated, In a Lettter to the Author of USURY STATED.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> for <hi>Jonathan Robinſon</hi> at the Golden Lion in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:30287:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:30287:2"/>
            <head>The Caſe of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury further debated.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Perceive by your <hi>Preface,</hi> that you do very well approve of <hi>a modeſt Inquiry concerning making Gain of Loan, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and how far it may be lawful:</hi> which being ſo requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to divers good Ends and Purpoſes you do inſtance in, I hope, as I do not condemn your Deſign, ſo you will incline to judg as favourably of mine, which is, <hi>That there may be yet ſome further Inquiry made into this Subject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>The Practice thereof hath gotten an ill Name, and you think there is ground enough to fear that there are divers found no Strangers to the Practice, who do it with a doubting Conſcience, as not fully ſatisfied in the Lawfulneſs of the thing practis'd.</hi> In order to whoſe Satisfaction (as alſo for the vindicating of many ſober and conſciencious Chriſtians from the Aſperſions they lie under upon this ſcore) you have called in the help of ſeveral modern learned Writers, to make it appear that what you plead for, is neither ſo ſtrange nor uncouth as ſome would obtrude upon the Wold's belief, and that (as the <hi>Roman</hi> Orator obſerved) <hi>it often comes to paſs, that what was generally counted diſgraceful, may in time be found not to be ſo:</hi> which Obſervation you mention again in Page 119, altho it ſeems to imply a kind of tacit Acknowledgment, that Uſury has been <hi>generally accounted diſgraceful</hi> heretofore. But for my part I have no deſign to caſt any diſgrace upon it; I judg as honourably of thoſe who are for the lawfulneſs of it, as of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30287:3"/>thoſe who are againſt it. There are and have been eminent Men for Learning and Piety of both Perſwaſions. I am as great an Enemy as your ſelf can be to all kind of Unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Aſperſions; and therefore ſhall not undertake the leaſt Defence of them; but do wiſh the late Author of <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer caſt,</hi> and all thoſe who either write or diſcourſe at that rate, would better examine their Zeal, and not ſuffer it to break forth into ſuch high and unaccountable Strains. Yea indeed I think there was very great reaſon to let ſuch Perſons underſtand that they are over-haſty in paſſing ſuch Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on their Brethren, who do only differ from them in ſo diſputable a matter. But foraſmuch as it is doubtful to many, and does yet remain ſtill ſo to me, notwithſtanding your <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply</hi> to the foreſaid Author, and the <hi>Animadverſions</hi> adjoyned, I conceive it will not be improper to make an Attempt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there may not be ſome further Satisfaction given to it.</p>
            <p>And in order hereunto, I ſhall firſt of all take notice, that in <hi>Page</hi> 2. you cite the <hi>pious and learned Vines</hi> inſtancing in Uſury, as that <hi>which is indeed very doubtful whether it be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly a Sin or no:</hi> and hereupon I find in his Treatiſe on the Lord's Supper, he concludes that this is not a ſufficient ground to debar any Perſon from the Communion of the Church. I am altogether of the ſame Opinion; but if it be <hi>very doubtful whether it be a Sin or no,</hi> I think it is the ſafeſt way not to meddle with it.</p>
            <p>You cite Mr. <hi>Dixon</hi> (Pag. 5.) declaring his Opinion on Pſal. 15.5. <hi>That there was a judicial diſpenſing with Commodity put upon the Jews in divers Caſes, whereof this was one, that they ſhould not take <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury of a Jew, but of other Country-men they might.</hi> They might indeed from a <hi>Stranger,</hi> Deut. 23.20. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto a Stranger thou mayſt lend upon <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury:</hi> but it does not certainly follow from thence, that we may lend upon Uſury one to another. Thoſe accurſed Nations who were devoted to Deſtruction, are called <hi>Strangers</hi> in the ſame Book of <hi>Deut.</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:30287:3"/>and there are divers Perſons of great Eminency, if not the greater number of Expoſitors, who underſtand that place to be meant of ſuch Strangers only. Arguments are offered on both hands, but they do not conclude certainly either one way or the other. Since then there is no manifeſt Evidence that the word <hi>Stranger</hi> in <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.20. takes in all others beſides the Jews, a Man may have reaſon to be afraid of meddling with Uſury, notwithſtanding all the Probabilities produced for your Interpretation of that place. Yea this O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, <hi>That the Law againſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury concerned the Jews only,</hi> whatever Probabilities it has to plead for it, yet was not, I am apt to think, the Opinion of our late Aſſembly of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines (whom your ſelf, I believe, bear a high regard to the Memory of, whatever others ſay of them) for I find in their <hi>larger Catechiſm</hi> they have reckon'd in Uſury among thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Sins forbidden in the 8th Commandment,</hi> and they prove it from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.5. <hi>He that putteth not out his Mony to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, &amp;c.</hi> the very ſame Text which you obſerve to be the ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work of Mr. <hi>J</hi>'s Diſcourſe. But if it were granted that the word <hi>Stranger</hi> extends to all others beſides the Jews, yet how doth it appear to be any more than a <hi>Toleration,</hi> or a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of <hi>Fact,</hi> not of <hi>Right.</hi> And to this Conſtruction the Annotations commonly called, <hi>The Aſſemblies Annotations,</hi> do incline, as you may ſee on <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.20. [unto a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger] <hi>This was permitted for a time, partly for the Hardneſs of their Hearts, as Bills of Divorce.</hi> And in the ſame Volume of Annotations on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.5. <hi>[He that putteth not out his Mony to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury]</hi> you have theſe Words, <hi>To one that was a Stranger they might put Money to uſe, that was permitted. What from hence may be gathered, or whether any thing at all to make it lawful among Chriſtians, thoſe that have written of this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy at large may be conſulted.</hi> Thus you may ſee this matter is not put out of doubt ſo plainly, as to incourage any one to build much upon it. I ſhall add hereunto, that the Uſury
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30287:4"/>which God's Law condemned, does in the Original ſignify <hi>biting,</hi> as all do grant: from whence, tho I do not plead that it certainly follows, yet at leaſt it may ſeem to ſome the more probable, that the Uſury there forbidden was an Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and if ſo, that then it does concern us now.</p>
            <p>As to the diſtinction between <hi>Intereſt</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> which you call a <hi>Nicety,</hi> pag. 7. it may poſſibly ſeem ſo to you: but the diſtinction is ſolid and rational enough in the Judgment of many worthy <hi>Caſuiſts,</hi> the one being an overplus for Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney <hi>lent,</hi> (which Act of <hi>lending,</hi> they plead to be in its own nature a <hi>liberal</hi> Act, and conſequently that it is a perverting thereof to make it <hi>mercenary</hi>) and the other for Money un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duly detained againſt a Man's Will to his Damage. You produce <hi>Grotius</hi> arguing againſt this Diſtinction thus, <hi>That then it ſhall be lawful thus to covenant, unleſs you repay within three days, you ſhall give ſo much for delay.</hi> But this I conceive will not invalidate the Diſtinction; for they who condemn Uſury, do ſay, If a Man do lend only for three days in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to one with whom he intends to leave it longer, and ſhall then take Profit for the Borrowers keeping of it all the reſt of the time beyond thoſe three days, he does but trifle indeed, and impoſe on his own Conſcience, which is privy to what he did ſecretly mean and intend; and in ſo doing he is as truly a Uſurer as if there were no ſuch pretence made.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Definitions</hi> of Uſury, which you repreſent as very various; ſome placing it in <hi>exacting</hi> Gain, others in the <hi>Compact</hi> or <hi>Covenant,</hi> and he whom you reply to in the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation,</hi> which you ſeem to wonder at moſt, <hi>Pag.</hi> 9. they do all come much to one and the ſame, according to the common and uſual Definition of Uſury, ſc. <hi>pactum ex mutuo Lucrum, Covenanting for Gain upon the account of Loan.</hi> Which Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant may be either expreſt or implied. And this latter way of covenanting may help you to the meaning of thoſe Words [<hi>expected,</hi> or <hi>intended</hi>] which you ſay you underſtand not,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30287:4"/>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 11. as alſo the <hi>taking</hi> what is not <hi>exacted,</hi> but only <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected,</hi> whereat you ſeem greatly amus'd, <hi>Pag.</hi> 137. When 'tis well known, and taken for granted by both Parties, that ſomething over and above the Money lent is <hi>expected</hi> or <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended</hi> in conſideration of the Loan, tho it be not <hi>actually ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed,</hi> this is an <hi>implicit Covenant.</hi> Mr. <hi>Fenton</hi> expreſſeth this Diſtinction thus, <hi>There is mental and actual <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury; the firſt conſiſteth only in the Intention of the Heart, for he that doth not indent either by Word or Deed, yet if any hope or expectation of Gain was to him a Motive of lending, that Man in the Court of Conſcience ſtandeth guilty of this Sin before God; as he that lock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on a Woman to luſt after her, commiteth Adultery with her in his Heart.</hi> And ſo Mr. <hi>Wilſon</hi> ſtates it in theſe Words, <hi>As the very deſire and expectation of Gain for lending only, is mental and intentional <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury; ſo the impoſing, or by Covenant before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand agreeing for Increaſe above the Principal, is of the nature of actual <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> After the ſame manner Mr. <hi>Greenhill</hi> ſtates it in his Expoſition on <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.8. and cites theſe Words of St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> for it, <hi>Si plus quàm dediſti expectas accipere, faenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor es.</hi> 'Twould be almoſt endleſs to quote Authors to this purpoſe; I will therefore inſtance but in one more, and that is the learned <hi>Ames,</hi> whom you have your ſelf referr'd to in divers places of your Book; and 'tis ſomewhat ſtrange methinks that you ſhould overlook the very Definition he gives of Uſury, which is, <hi>Lucrum ex mutuo quaeſitum vi ipſius mutui:</hi> which word <hi>quaeſitum</hi> he explains thus, <hi>Quaeſitum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur hoc lucrum, non Conventum; quià non tantùm uſura realis, in quâ pactum intercedit, ſed &amp; mentalis quae verſatur in Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione Lucrum ut debitum ex mutuo acquirendi, iſtâ Deſcriptione contineatur.</hi> He tells you alſo that thoſe words, <hi>vi ipſius mutui,</hi> are added to diſtinguiſh <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> from <hi>Intereſt.</hi> To this Head may be referr'd what you ſay, <hi>Pag.</hi> 133. when Mr. <hi>J.</hi> pleads that the taking of a Gift for Loan is Uſury, if the Gift were <hi>intended</hi> or <hi>expected;</hi> you reply, <hi>Let Reaſon judg, where it is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30287:5"/>ſinful to expect a Gift, is it not ſinful alſo to receive it?</hi> I do not ſee how it is at all contrary to Reaſon, that a Man may warrantably receive what he ought not to expect. I lend my Money freely, as a pure act of Love and Kindneſs, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting nothing for the Loan: If he that has borrow'd it, will of his own Ingenuity and Gratitude, put me upon recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſome Gift from him which I did not look for, the Caſe is different from what it would have been, if I had look'd for it, and from the hopes thereof had been influenced to lend him this Money. And to this purpoſe I ſhall obſerve to you what <hi>Ames</hi> hath determin'd concerning <hi>Simony,</hi> which may give ſome light to the preſent Caſe; <hi>Non eſt Simonia, quando ex merâ Gratitudine, ſine ullo pacto expreſſo, vel tacito, directè vel indirectè, aliquid datur. At</hi> intentio ipſa <hi>iſtiuſmodi donationum aut receptionum, quamvis in alterâ ſolâ parte conſiſtat, eſt gradus quidam hujus peccati, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> adeò non malè vocatur Simonia</hi> Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis, <hi>&amp; à nonnullis</hi> confidentialis, <hi>prout diſtinguitur à conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionali &amp; reali.</hi> You ſee then the learned <hi>Ames</hi> did judg a Man may without the Guilt of <hi>Simony,</hi> receive what it would have been Simony in him to <hi>expect.</hi> So they who hold it Uſury to <hi>expect</hi> a Gift for Loan, count it not ſo to receive it afterwards if it come unexpected.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adventuring</hi> is eaſily enough diſtinguiſhable from <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> tho you ſeem very loth to acknowledg it; and ſuppoſing the Conſideration for it be moderate and proportionable to the hazard, it has never I think been condemn'd by any judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and conſidering Perſon; being a Co-partnerſhip with another that adventures upon the like hazard with himſelf of the Ships miſcarrying: If the Ship be loſt, all is loſt. So ſay you, <hi>The Lenders Principal is loſt if the Debtor break.</hi> But is this the like hazard with the former? The hazard you men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Perſon's breaking,</hi> is in this caſe of Adventure too, beſides the hazard of the Ship's return: for the Man who is intruſted with the Money that is adventur'd, may
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:30287:5"/>break, and ſometimes does. But the Profit received upon the Ship's return is not in Conſideration of that hazard of the Man's breaking, but of the known hazard to which the Ship is expos'd, and the proportionable Returns the Ship is like to make if it comes home ſafe. There is ſome Uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty in all worldly things: but they who lend upon Uſe, do take care to ſecure their Money <hi>abſolutely,</hi> either by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Land bound for it, or by ſome collateral perſonal Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, or both. They may be ſometimes miſtaken when they think it very ſure, and there is no worldly thing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever but is liable to ſome Caſualty. It may ſuffice to this purpoſe, that the Uſurer means no other than to place it in good and ſufficient and ſure Hands: 'Twere not free from all Caſualty, if he did chuſe to keep it in his own.</p>
            <p>You ſay further, <hi>Pag.</hi> 17. or rather quote <hi>Rivet</hi> for it, <q>That what is cited out of <hi>Ariſtotle, Cicero, Plutarch,</hi> &amp;c. againſt Uſury, reſpects not ſo much what is intrinſecal, as what is accidental, and commonly attends it. The like may be ſaid of the Expreſſions of the Fathers which are very bitter againſt Uſury, they had reſpect to that Uſury which prevailed too much in all Ages againſt Equity, Honeſty, Charity and Faithfulneſs; as <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> upon <hi>Matthew</hi> ſaid, There was nothing more cruel, nothing more ſhameful than the Uſury of his Time: but it follows not that they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood it of all Uſury, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Did thoſe learned Men and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers thers themſelves make any Diſtinction, and ſay, They meant what they ſpake of <hi>ſome <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurers only?</hi> If not, 'tis but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the moſt uſual and ordinary way of Conſtruction to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury in common;</hi> and to ſuppoſe the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſeems very precarious: And ſo does your following Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Sayings of the Heathens that are ſo rigid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Uſury, <hi>Pag.</hi> 18. You find, you ſay, in <hi>Seneca,</hi> a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rule for the right underſtanding of ſuch like Paſſages, <hi>ſc.</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Some things</hi> are commanded beyond meaſure, that they may
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:30287:6"/>return to their proper and right meaſure, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And as often as there is little Confidence in thoſe things thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireſt, more muſt be injoyned than is ſufficient, that what is ſufficient may be performed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> This general Rule you have found out would do ſpecial Service, if it were applied to all thoſe Purpoſes to which it is applicable, as to this of Uſury.</p>
            <p>The next thing I ſhall obſerve to you is, your appealing to <hi>godly Perkins,</hi> Pag. 26. and Pag. 203. <q>
                  <hi>Hear bleſſed</hi> Calvin, <hi>and let</hi> Grotius <hi>moderate between us,</hi> Pag. 143. What if he that writes againſt Uſury ſhould ſay, <hi>I appeal to godly</hi> Bolton, <hi>or hear bleſſed Biſhop</hi> Jewel, <hi>or let Biſhop</hi> Sanderſon <hi>moderate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us,</hi> would you take thoſe to be Arbitrators in this caſe?</q> And whereas you add further, <q>That you dare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouch ſuch as having Wealth in their Coffers, and there let it lie idle, having fair and honeſt Opportunities to bring the ſame forth, are none of the beſt Members in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, <hi>Pag.</hi> 33.</q> I know no Man will gain-ſay you; you need not doubt of being poſitive in this. But in another place, methinks <hi>your poſitive Concluſion</hi> may admit of ſome De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur. Sc. <hi>Pag.</hi> 92. <q>What Mr. <hi>J.</hi> ſaith, &amp;c. avails nothing; for upon Suppoſition that the Law it ſelf [<hi>ſc.</hi> againſt Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry] be not political and proper to the Jews, but univerſal, and in its full force unto this day; I ſay, that Uſury in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is forbidden only with reſpect to the Poor.</q> I ſee you are reſolv'd to carry the Cauſe one way or other. If one Interpretation will not hold, this other ſhall. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I make any Reply to that, it may not be amiſs to take notice of thoſe manifold Expoſitions you produce of that Text, <hi>Luke</hi> 6.35. <hi>Lend, hoping for nothing again.</hi> Firſt, that it may be underſtood of <hi>free giving:</hi> And to ſtrengthen this Opinion, you compare <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.21. <hi>The Righteous ſheweth Mercy, and giveth;</hi> with <hi>ver.</hi> 26. <hi>He is ever merciful, and lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth:</hi> both which you think to be one and the ſame, and that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:30287:6"/>
               <hi>free giving</hi> is called <hi>lending,</hi> becauſe of the Retribution that God ſhall make unto thoſe, who thus communicate their Goods: for we learn from <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.17. that, <hi>He that giveth to the Poor, lendeth to the Lord.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Hoping for nothing again: i. e.</hi> tho you have little reaſon to hope for the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal, becauſe of the Poverty of the Debtor, whoſe Neceſſity may require that we lend to him, tho we have juſt cauſe to doubt he will not be able to repay it: And by ſo doing, we ſhall exceed thoſe Sinners mention'd <hi>ver.</hi> 34. who <hi>lend to Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to receive as much again.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Hoping for nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: i. e.</hi> fruſtrating none that come to borrow, of that hope which they have conceived of your Beneficence. Lend, and fruſtrate not the hope of any. If any have need of Loan, be not ſo rigid towards them, as to cut off all hope of a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit to be conferred, but rather ſhew your ſelves forward in lending. Fourthly, <hi>Hoping for nothing again: i. e.</hi> not hoping to receive the like Kindneſs again, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>aequalia,</hi> as ſuppoſe the having of the like Sum lent to you another time. Fifthly, <hi>Hoping for nothing again: i. e.</hi> deſparing nothing, or not loſing all manner of hope, <hi>viz.</hi> of a juſt Retribution from God, if not from Man. Here are divers Interpretations of this Text, and yet you ſpeak of paſſing by others. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed you have paſt by one as plauſible as moſt of thoſe you have mention'd; and the Opinion too of an Expoſitor you have in your Book quoted oftneſt of all; which is, that our Saviour ſheweth <hi>with what Affection and Diſpoſition of Heart Men ought to lend,</hi> viz. <hi>Having reſpect to the good of the Party borrowing, and not to the Reſtitution of the thing lent.</hi> But how many Interpretations ſoever the Text is <hi>favourably capable of,</hi> as you expreſs it, <hi>Pag.</hi> 43. yet from hence it doth appear, that thoſe who underſtand not this Text of expecting <hi>beyond the Principal,</hi> are not agreed among themſelves concerning the Senſe of it, but of very various Minds what Conſtruction to make thereof. And yet I believe, put them all together, it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:30287:7"/>will be found that the greater number of Expoſitors who have written on this Text, do go the other way, and do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it of lending, without expectation of any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Principal in Conſideration of the Loan. If it be probable that theſe latter are miſtaken, yet it does not certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear that they are ſo: and poſſibly their underſtanding of that place does bid as fair as ſome of the Gloſſes you have produced. But what if it ſhould be granted that Uſury is not particularly condemned in the New Teſtament? May it not ſuffice, that it is condemned by <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, and the Book of Pſalms? where do we find falſe Weights and Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, or Perjury particularly forbidden in the N. Teſt.? If you ſay, falſe Weights and Meaſures are forbidden in the N. Teſt. under the general name of Injuſtice; ſo it may be ſaid that Uſury is forbidden under the general name of Uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or Oppreſſion: But divers there are, who believe this Text to have a particular reſpect to Uſury. You add, <q>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it be granted, that <hi>hoping for nothing again,</hi> reſpects the Uſe or Overplus, this may be, and yet with Reſtriction to the Poor, even as, <hi>give to every Man that asketh of thee, ver.</hi> 30. muſt be reſtrained to ſuch as are fit Objects of our Alms; and why ſhould not, <hi>Lend, hoping for nothing again,</hi> have its Reſtrictions too?</q> I anſwer, ſo it will admit of the like Reſtrictions with the former, and yet be underſtood to condemn taking any Overplus for the Loan from any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: For no one pleads that we are bound to lend to all Perſons that would borrow of us whatever they have a mind to borrow, but only to ſuch as we judg fit Objects to lend unto; and whatever we do ſo lend, to lend the ſame freely, without agreeing either directly, or indirectly, to receive back any thing again over and above what we do lend.</p>
            <p>As to what <hi>you wiſh, that ſome would take notice of another ſort of Theft,</hi> Pag. 52. 'Tis a Reflection remote and alien from the caſe in hand; for which Reaſon I ſhall make no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:30287:7"/>Obſervation on it, than that I conceive, if what is inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated be true, it had been however more candid and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous to have referr'd that to ſome private Admonition.</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>Pag.</hi> 54. that Mr. <hi>J</hi>'s Triumph which he makes from the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> conſiſting of 318 holy Men, &amp;c. amounts to no more than this, <hi>Whoever of the Clergy for filthy Lucre ſake exerciſeth <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, let him be depoſed:</hi> And ſo you paſs on in your Diſcourſe without any other Reply to it, as if this of the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> had been ſcarce worth the mentioning.</p>
            <p>But I am loth to be tedious, and therefore ſhall paſs to the <hi>ſecond Anſwer</hi> you give, which is, that <hi>if the Law againſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury were not political and proper to the Jews, then you ſay that it did forbid it only with reſpect to the Poor.</hi> In ſome places in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Poor are mention'd: but in divers other places, and the greateſt number too, there is no mention made of the Poor. The Reply you make to this, for which you refer to Mr. <hi>Baxter's Directory,</hi> is, that where the Prophets reprove the Sin of Uſury, it is expreſſed without that Limitation of the Poor, <q>Partly becauſe it ſuppoſeth the meaning of the Law to be known, which the Prophets did but apply; and partly becauſe there was little or no lending uſed among the Jews but to the needy, as an Act of Charity.</q> The firſt Reaſon is only a Conjecture, taking that for granted, which is the very matter in diſpute, ſc. <hi>That it was generally known that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury was limited to the Poor.</hi> And if this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture be right, then it muſt follow that it was lawful for one Jew to take uſe of another Jew that was rich; and then your firſt Defence will fall to the ground. The ſecond Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may as ſtrongly be urged on the contrary part, <hi>viz.</hi> therefore the word <hi>Poor</hi> was added to <hi>Brother</hi> in ſome Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures where Uſury is condemn'd, becauſe the Poor were the Perſons moſtly concerned in borrowing: which you do grant your ſelf in theſe Words, <hi>Pag.</hi> 231. <hi>Moſtly it was the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30287:8"/>poorer ſort among the Jews that borrowed.</hi> And you alſo quote Mr. <hi>Capel</hi> for it, ſaying, <hi>The Law doth urge it most that it be not done to the poor Jews, becauſe the Jews were not wont to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, except it were the poorer ſort.</hi> And this Conſtruction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees well with other Scriptures, particularly <hi>Deut.</hi> 24.14. <hi>Thou ſhalt not oppreſs an hired Servant that is poor and needy:</hi> 'Twill not follow that they might oppreſs others. And <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.22, &amp;c. <hi>Ye ſhall not afflict any Widow or Fatherleſs Child, &amp;c.</hi> And in the very next place it follows, <hi>If thou lend Money to any of my People that is poor by thee, thou ſhalt not be to him as an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer, neither ſhalt thou lay upon him <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> 'Twill not follow that if they did lend Money to any of their Brethren that were rich, they might lay Uſury upon them. Yea, many who think Uſury lawful now, do grant that it was unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for the Jews to take Uſe of their Brethren, tho they were rich. You produce <hi>Rivet,</hi> Pag. 94. <q>Replying, that in ſuch Conſequences there is a Diſſimilitude, becauſe Oppreſſion and the like are evil in themſelves, as is clearly proved from other places; but it is not evil in it ſelf to take any Increaſe for Loan, but in ſome caſes only, into which the rich Man while ſuch falleth not.</q> But how does it appear that Uſury is not evil in it ſelf? He ſays ſo 'tis true, and makes that a Reaſon to invalidate the former Conſequences: but this is the thing under queſtion, and therefore I conceive not to be taken for granted in the Diſpute concerning it. 'Tis ſufficient to the preſent purpoſe, that what is evil in it ſelf, may be ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>with a Limitation annexed,</hi> tho the thing notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding be <hi>evil univerſally:</hi> even ſo, tho Uſury be forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in ſome places with a Limitation to the Poor, yet it will not follow from thence but it may be evil univerſally? 'Tis an aggravation of any Oppreſſion, if it be a poor Man that is oppreſſed; as it was a more heinous Offence to take the poor Man's Lamb who had nothing elſe ſave that one Ewe-Lamb which he had nouriſhed up with his Children, than to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:30287:8"/>have taken one from a rich Man, who had many and could well ſpare it: but the Aggravation of ſuch an Oppreſſion will not ſerve to juſtify any other of a leſs degree. You plead very much in divers places of your Book for the <hi>Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableneſs</hi> of ſome kind of Uſury, and urge this, that <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Money is worth Money, and as valuable as that for which we receive Rent.</hi> But if God have forbidden the receiving Profit for Loan, which is the matter in queſtion, 'tis not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for us to ſay that <hi>Loan is valuable.</hi> You grant that God hath forbidden us to take uſe of a <hi>poor Man,</hi> if we lend him a Sum of Money to ſerve his Occaſions, and yet my lending him this Sum of Money is as <hi>valuable</hi> in it ſelf as my lending the like Sum to a <hi>rich Man.</hi> Why may I not then (if our Judgment concerning the <hi>Equitableneſs</hi> of the thing may ſerve) take Uſe of this <hi>poor Man</hi> for that which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed as valuable? or why may I not take Profit of him for the Loan of Money, if it be altogether as valuable, and it be no more <hi>evil in it ſelf</hi> (to take Uſe than to take Rent) as well as take Rent of him for my Houſe wherein he lives? What Injuſtice is there in the former more than in the latter? You will poſſibly ſay, 'tis a breach of <hi>Charity</hi> to make a <hi>poor Man</hi> pay Uſe for Loan, tho the Loan be valuable: But can you give me a reaſon why Charity ſhould oblige me to give him the Conſideration for the Loan, more than the Conſideration for his dwelling in my Houſe, both of them being equally valuable, unleſs you produce this Divine Law againſt Uſury? And if you do ſo, then you muſt plead that it is in force now with reſpect to the Poor, and ſo much of it is moral; but with reſpect to the Rich it is not in force, that being judicial, (thus making it partly moral, and partly judicial) or that it was never intended at all but only with reſpect to the Poor. But is not this a very doubtful and uncertain way of concluding; and the rather, for that the great Argument of <hi>Equity</hi> holds with reſpect to the Poor as well as the Rich? If it be as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitable
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30287:9"/>that a poor Man ſhould pay me ten Shillings Rent for his poor Dwelling, as that the rich Man (who is my Tenant alſo) ſhould pay me ten Pound Rent for his Houſe, being of anſwerable value; why it is not as equitable that the poor Man ſhould pay me Uſe for five Pound, as that the rich Man ſhould pay me Uſe for five hundred? I may indeed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline rather to <hi>give</hi> the poor Man his Uſe, and ſo I may to give him his Houſe-Rent: but according to the ſtrict Rules of Juſtice and Equity, I ſee not the Difference; for the poor Man hath as valuable a Conſideration for the Uſe he pays, as the rich Man hath for the Uſe that is paid by him; and the Conſideration too is as valuable for the Uſe he pays me, as for the Rent he pays me, the Loan of Money being in it ſelf as truly valuable as the letting of an Houſe. From all which it appears, that we are not in all Caſes to bring God's Laws to <hi>our Meaſures,</hi> and that there is but little Reaſon to build much upon either of theſe Concluſions, That the Law is moral in one reſpect, and not in the other; or that it was primarily intended only with reſpect to the Poor.</p>
            <p>And now having ſhewed, that <hi>theſe Limitations</hi> applied to thoſe Scriptures that condemn Uſury, are not ſo ſatisfactory as to put this matter out of doubt, that the Uſury you pleaded for is lawful, I ſhall apply my ſelf to thoſe principal Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments before me, which you offer in defence of it. And thoſe may be reduced to theſe <hi>ſeven</hi> following, which I ſhall ſpeak to in the order I ſet them down, tho they be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe placed in your Book, according as Mr. <hi>J</hi>'s Diſcourſe gave you occaſion to offer them.</p>
            <list>
               <item>And the firſt is, That it is not <hi>biting,</hi> becauſe the Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower as well as the Lender may be a Gainer by it.</item>
               <item>Secondly; That the Law of the Land is for it.</item>
               <item>Thirdly; That a Man is not bound to lend his Stock free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to thoſe who are as rich or richer than himſelf.</item>
               <item>Fourthly; That many Holy and Learned Men have judged it lawful.</item>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:30287:9"/>
               <item>Fifthly; That it is neceſſary to the carrying on of Trade.</item>
               <item>Sixthly; That it is but doing as you would be done by.</item>
               <item>Seventhly; That there are divers Caſes, ſome of which you inſtance in, wherein 'tis hard to make it appear that U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury is more biting than other ways of dealing, that are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd of by thoſe who condemn Uſury. I ſhall reply to each of theſe in their order.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Your firſt Argument is commonly anſwer'd by divers In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances which are given of unwarrantable dealings, wherein yet both Parties are Gainers, among which I ſhall only men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this one, <hi>ſc.</hi> buying a Preſentation. You anſwer to this, that tho both Parties be Gainers thereby, yet the Church is a Loſer: ſo 'tis return'd to your Argument; tho both Lender and Borrower may be Gainers, yet thoſe Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers who buy of thoſe Men that borrow upon Uſe, are bitten; and that they muſt pay the dearer for what they buy; other Tradeſmen who have Monies of their own, being as willing generally to raiſe the Price too, and ſell as dear as they can. And for this reaſon they who have writ againſt Uſury, conclude all Uſury to be biting; whether de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly or no, I will not ſay; but this is moſt plain in their Writings, that they will not admit this Diſtinction of a <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate</hi> Uſury and a <hi>biting</hi> Uſury. And for this reaſon you might have ſpar'd me-thinks what I find <hi>Pag.</hi> 134. Mr. <hi>J.</hi> anſwers thoſe who plead that the Expreſſions of the Fathers, and other Writers by him quoted againſt Uſury, were to be underſtood of <hi>griping</hi> Uſury, that there was no ſuch matter. You reply upon him, <hi>Are they then to be underſtood of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury that is not griping? we muſt pardon his Memory having told us before once and again, that all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury was griping.</hi> Pray conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what kind of arguing this is. Was it not very obvious that Mr. <hi>J.</hi> meant no more than this, that what the Fathers and thoſe Writers he quoted, condemn'd, was Uſury conſidered without this Diſtinction of <hi>griping</hi> Uſury and <hi>moderate</hi> Uſury?
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:30287:10"/>You indeed make this Diſtinction for them divers times, but they have made no ſuch themſelves. Dr. <hi>John Raynolds</hi> (than whom, as one obſerves, the World hardly ever ſaw a better Man, and a better Scholar) concluded this diſtinction of <hi>bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> Uſury, and not <hi>biting,</hi> (made uſe of, ſaith he, by ſome late Divines) to be but a meer flam. And to the like purpoſe, ſays Mr. <hi>Greenkill</hi> in his Expoſition on <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.8. <q>Let Men take heed how they meddle with Uſury, and truſt to a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of Man's Brain, making biting Uſury unlawful, and other Uſury lawful; leſt by this Diſtinction they get Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in their Coffers, and loſe their Souls at laſt.</q> The ſame I find in the Engliſh Annotations on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.5. <hi>The common diſtinction of biting and more moderate <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, hath no ground at all in Scripture,</hi> &amp;c. Much of your Diſcourſe depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Diſtinction; whereas if there were any ſuch intended in the Law, then you muſt grant, I conceive, that 'twas on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what you call <hi>biting <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> that was forbidden to the Jews, and not that which you call <hi>moderate <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> And if ſo, I would ask you this Queſtion, Whether you think the Jews might practiſe this kind of biting Uſury towards all Strangers, that is to ſay, towards all thoſe that were not Jews? If you admit that, it muſt be conſidered how we are to underſtand thoſe Scriptures, in which God requir'd the Jews to ſhew Mercy and Kindneſs to Strangers. Indeed by this Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you ſeem to hold the Jews and us to be equally concern'd in this Law and Command of God againſt Uſury, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently invalidate your firſt Defence, That this <hi>Law was political and peculiar to the Jewiſh Nation.</hi> The word in the Original for Uſury ſignifies <hi>biting,</hi> becauſe, ſaith <hi>Junius,</hi> U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury biteth and conſumeth a Man and his Subſtance. And ſo ſaith <hi>Ainſworth,</hi> and I believe moſt others that treat of it. But what a weak Foundation is this to ground ſuch a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction upon, becauſe the word ſignifies <hi>biting,</hi> that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is a <hi>twofold</hi> Uſury, <hi>biting,</hi> and <hi>not biting?</hi> Eſpecially
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:30287:10"/>ſeeing not only <hi>Neſhek,</hi> which ſignifies <hi>biting,</hi> but <hi>Tarbith,</hi> which ſignifies <hi>Increaſe,</hi> is condemn'd, <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.36. and both mention'd together, <hi>Take thou no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury of him or Increaſe, but fear thy God.</hi> And <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.13. <hi>Hath given forth upon <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and hath taken Increaſe, ſhall he then live? &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your <hi>ſecond Argument</hi> I find, <hi>Pag.</hi> 103. where you plead the Law on your ſide for the the taking of Uſe, which Mr. <hi>J.</hi> ſuppoſing the Law to admit for the avoiding of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Evils, you ſeem to wonder at that much. <hi>Greater Evils! what greater than the Damnation of Souls? I can't believe it.</hi> Do you not believe that the <hi>leaſt Oppreſſion</hi> (taking Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in that ſence which all do allow of) does deſerve Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation? and do you not alſo believe that ſome Oppreſſions are greater than others? If it be an Oppreſſion to require <hi>ſix Pound</hi> for the Loan of an hundred, (which ſome do think it is) 'tis a greater Oppreſſion in the like Circumſtances to require <hi>eight</hi> or <hi>ten.</hi> But as to this Argument of the Law's being on your ſide, it will not be amiſs to take a little no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of your own way of expreſſing it, <hi>Pag.</hi> 104. <q>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Law immediately preceding this which is now in force, allowed eight in the hundred, this laſt Statute <hi>forbids taking above ſix per Cent.</hi>
               </q> Which Toleration is granted, ſays the Learned <hi>Coke,</hi> that great Oracle of the Law, for the like reaſon that Divorce was tolerated among the Jews. Our Law does not incourage the taking of any Uſe, or undertake to juſtify it as warrantable in point of Conſcience, but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids taking more than ſix <hi>per Gent.</hi> Yea, the very <hi>Act of the 13th of Q.</hi> Eliz. concerning Uſury, begins thus, <hi>Foraſmuch as all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury forbidden by God, is Sin and deteſtable, &amp;c.</hi> And in the <hi>Statute of</hi> Jac. 21. there is this <hi>Proviſo,</hi> which you make reply to, <hi>Pag.</hi> 109. <hi>Provided that no words in this Law con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, ſhall be conſtrued or expounded to allow the practice of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury in point of Religion or Conſcience.</hi> And the Import of your Reply to it, I conceive to be this, That tho the Law do
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:30287:11"/>not allow the practice of Uſury in point of Religion or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; 'tis ſufficient that it doth allow it in civil Commerce; and that it appertained not to a Civil Court, as the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, to determine whether a Man may <hi>practiſe it in point of Conſcience or no:</hi> To which you add, <hi>If the Civil Law forbids Fleſh in Lent, the uſe thereof at that time in point of Conſcience remains lawful as before.</hi> Pray conſider how well you have follow'd your own Argument, and whether to apply your way of managing it to the caſe in hand, the Conſequence of it muſt not be this, That altho the Law allow the practice of Uſury in civil Commerce, the thing however in point of Conſcience is the ſame as it was before, notwithſtanding what the Law ſays of it either one way or other? And yet you ſeem to put a great Streſs upon the <hi>Law</hi> in this matter of Uſury, as if Conſcience might be influenc'd and ſatisfy'd thereby, and there were no difference between <hi>Legitimum</hi> and <hi>Licitum:</hi> particularly, p. 105. <q>Let it be conſider'd, foraſmuch as Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety receives its limitation and application from humane Laws, whether any Man hath not the ſame Right to Six <hi>per Cent.</hi> in this Land, that lends his Money, as any one has to his Lands and Tenements, or any Goods he enjoys, by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the Laws.</q> You may be pleaſed to remember that the Queſtion, <hi>Whether Gain covenanted for Loan be lawful or no?</hi> is not to be underſtood whether it be lawful by Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but by Divine Law. And you ſay with reference to the Law which forbids Fleſh in Lent, that the uſe thereof at that time in point of Conſcience remains lawful as before. What Obligation human Laws have on the Conſcience, needs not here to be diſputed; for the Law does not command a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Man to take Uſe. But to return to your Inſtance. If the Law forbidding Fleſh in Lent don't alter that caſe in point of Conſcience, how comes it to paſs that it ſhould have ſuch an Influence here in point of Conſcience? You ſay, <hi>Pag.</hi> 106. <hi>It appertains to theſe Laws to ſtate and appoint, as at what
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:30287:11"/>rate Gold and Silver ſhall be valuable, ſo alſo what rate Money lent ſhall bear.</hi> I would grant what you ſay, if there had been no more declar'd in Scripture concerning lending of Money, than there is at what rate Gold and Silver ſhall be valu'd. What you quote Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> for, <hi>Pag.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>5. reſpects ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Caſe far different from this, <hi>ſc.</hi> 
               <q>That Chriſt's Kingdom is not of this World, that he came not to interpoſe in Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Affairs (ſuch as are the Proprieties of Men) but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed having any thing to do to be a Judg or Divider among Men.</q> Are there no Rules then and Laws in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that concern human Contracts? Does God's Word no where interpoſe in Secular Affairs, but leave all to Man's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination? Our Saviour, while he was here, would not be a Judg, but keep to his own Calling: doth it thence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that the Law of God doth not interpoſe in Secular Affairs? Theſe Words of Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> are applied by him to confute thoſe who do found all Propriety in Grace, ſo as to juſtify all their Rapins and Invaſions on the Eſtates of thoſe whom they did look upon to be wicked, depriving them of their moſt lawful Rights and Poſſeſſions meerly upon this pretence, becauſe they were unholy; and laying claim thereto themſelves as being gracious Perſons, and thereby priviledg'd to enter upon, and take Poſſeſſion of any carnal Man's Inheritance. How little does this agree to the purpoſe you produce it for? And yet this ſame Argument you urge again, <hi>Pag.</hi> 247. and would prove it by this of Dr. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond.</hi> Do you think that there are not ſuch Laws in ſome Countries, or that there may not be ſuch a Law as will allow of unjuſt Gain? I mean, ſuch Gain as is forbidden by God's Word? And will not ſuch Gain remain ſinful and unwarran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſtill, notwithſtanding any human Law concerning it? If ſo, then this is no certain Rule, that a Man may ſafely take all that the Law will permit him to take. Yea, Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> himſelf, who holds Uſury lawful, to which purpoſe you
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:30287:12"/>have quoted him in divers places, yet among his Cautions lays down this, <hi>That it is the ſafeſt Courſe for him that puts out his Money, not to require all that he may by Law, but to keep within that which the Law permits.</hi> And Bp <hi>Taylor,</hi> whoſe Authority you have made uſe of, as a Favourer of your Cauſe, in his <hi>Ductor dubitantium,</hi> lib. 3. cap. 3. pag. 571. on Queſt. 5. <hi>Whether is to be obeyed, the Prince, or the Biſhop, if they happen to command contrary things?</hi> ſays, <q>The latter is to be obeyed, in caſe what the Civil Law enacts be only a <hi>Permiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and not a <hi>Sanction</hi> and <hi>Command:</hi> As where the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Laws forbid Marriage in a certain degree, and the Civil Power permits it, then the Subject may more ſafely obey the Power Eccleſiaſtical: for the Civil Power does not command to marry in a certain degree. So it is in ſuch things which are permitted for the Hardneſs of Mens Hearts, or the publick Neceſſity. The Permiſſion of the Prince is no Abſolution from the Authority of the Church. Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Uſury to be unlawful (as it is certain many kinds and Inſtances of it are highly criminal) yet the Civil Laws permit it, and the Church forbids it. In this caſe the Canons are to be preferr'd; for tho it be permitted, yet by the Laws no Man is compell'd to be an Uſurer, and therefore Men muſt pay that Reverence and Obedience which is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe due to them that have the Rule over them in the conduct of their Souls.</q> And whereas you plead, <hi>Pag.</hi> 103. <hi>That you can't be perſwaded that Men may take ſo much upon them as to tolerate or permit that which is in it ſelf unlawful, ſince 'twould be a virtual Diſpenſation for the breach of a Divine Law;</hi> I ſhall not preſume to offer my Thoughts in the Caſe; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they do well or no in tolerating it, is not that which I take to be the Queſtion we are principally concerned to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after, but whether we ſhall do well in practiſing it. However I ſhall give you the Opinion of this ſame great and eminent Caſuiſt in the ſame Book, <hi>Pag.</hi> 285. <hi>The Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:30287:12"/>may promiſe not to puniſh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, tho of it ſelf it were uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, and conſequently unlawful.</hi> So that as for this <hi>Learned Biſhop,</hi> tho he ſpeak with much Moderation on this Subject (and 'tis fit every one ſhould be moderate in ſuch diſputable matters) yet whoſo impartially weighs what he hath written concerning it, will have little Incouragement from thence to practiſe Uſury. But I deſire you yet further to conſider, If you hold only ſuch a kind of Uſury lawful, as your own Authors you quote do allow of, you muſt condemn ſuch U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury as is not qualified with thoſe <hi>Limitations</hi> and <hi>Reſtrictions</hi> that they lay down: but the Law of our Land which you do urge in this matter, and plead for the warrantableneſs of taking whatever it allows, does allow the taking of Uſury e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>from the Poor, and whether the Borrower gain any thing by it, or no,</hi> yea, <hi>tho he loſe the whole Principal;</hi> and conſequently to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerates that which is condemn'd by your own Authors. This Argument therefore from the Law will go further than you would have it. If you ſay, Tho the Law will ſuffer a Man to require Uſe in ſuch Caſes, yet however he is left to his own Conſcience in it, he may chuſe whether he will or no: So ſay I, he may chuſe whether he will take any Uſe at all or no. The Law leaves him to his own liberty and choice in the one as well as the other. Yea, 'tis the Opinion of Learned Men, that our Law-givers were fain to tolerate this thing, becauſe they knew not well how to reform it. I ſhall ſay no more at preſent concerning this Law of ours, ſave on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this, that it may be the leſs wonder'd at that there is ſuch a <hi>Proviſo</hi> in it, <hi>That no Words therein contained ſhall be conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or expounded to allow the practice of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury in point of Religion or Conſcience,</hi> not only becauſe 'tis againſt the general Current of Writers of all Profeſſions, but alſo becauſe it is contrary to the <hi>Doctrine of our Church,</hi> which was then (as it is ſtill) eſtabliſhed by Law in her Book of Homilies, where we have theſe Words, <hi>If the Merchant and worldly Occupier knew
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:30287:13"/>that God is the giver of Riches, he would content himſelf with ſo much as, by juſt means approved of God, he could get to his Living, and would be no richer than Truth would ſuffer him, he would never procure his Gain and ask his Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds at the Devils Hand. God forbid, ye will ſay, that any Man ſhould take his Riches of the Devil: Verily ſo many as increaſe themſelves by Vſury, by Extortion, by Perjury, by Stealth, by Deceits and Craft, they have their Goods of the Devil's Gift, &amp;c.</hi> Hom. for Rogation-Week, <hi>2d</hi> Part.</p>
            <p>Your third Argument above-mention'd is, <hi>That a Man is not bound to lend his ſtock freely to thoſe who are as rich or richer than himſelf.</hi> But this is very eaſily to be anſwer'd, <hi>viz.</hi> that there are divers other ways of laying out a ſtock of Money, beſides putting it to uſe; which is ſo obvious, that I do the more wonder at what you write, <hi>Pag.</hi> 208. <q>If in all Caſes, and to all Perſons we are tied up to uſe Acts of pure Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, there would be no room left for Acts of Juſtice; ſuch as buying and ſelling, for giving, and free lending would ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low up all the former Acts.</q> Did ever Mr. <hi>Bolton,</hi> whom you are now anſwering, or Mr. <hi>Capel</hi> (whom you afterwards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow ſome Animadverſions upon) or any Perſon elſe that hath written againſt Uſury, lay down any ſuch thing, that we muſt give or lend away all our Money, ſo as there ſhould be no room left for buying or ſelling? And yet, which is more ſtrange, you proceed to offer Reaſons againſt this, which I think no Perſon in the World ever ſaid or intended. Your firſt Reaſon is, <q>If a Man were tied up to Acts of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ;and were not free to uſe Acts of Juſtice in Contracts, then the Fountain of his Charity would ſoon be drawn dry: for then he would be ſtill laying out, but not taking in; and no Man is able to ſatisfy the Cravings and Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of all neceſſitous Perſons, much leſs of all ſuch as would borrow freely.</q> 'Tis very ſure, and this one Reaſon
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:30287:13"/>is abundantly ſufficient to prove what no body will deny: But however you proceed to a ſecond, which is, <q>That Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity injoyns us not to be cruel to our Selves or Relations; tho we are to be kind to others, yet not ſo as to be unkind to our ſelves.</q> Did ever any Man plead that we are bound to lend all that we have to others, or ſo much as will diſable us from making ſuch competent Proviſion as our Conditions and Relations do require? Yea, inſtead hereof you bring in Mr. <hi>Capel</hi> himſelf, ſaying the ſame with you; and 'twould be wonderful ſtrange if he were not of your Mind in this thing. <hi>I ſpeak</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Capel</hi>) <hi>of ſuch as are able, for we may not ſtretch beyond our Staple, and ſpoil all. I muſt not make my ſelf poor, to keep another from being poor, &amp;c.</hi> But I ſhall not proceed hereon any further to the exerciſe of your Patience.</p>
            <p>Your fourth Argument above-mention'd, <hi>That many holy and learned Men have judg'd it lawful,</hi> does fully convince me that there is great Reaſon to judg charitably and honourably of thoſe who are ſo perſwaded: but it does not prove the Lawfulneſs of it any more, than that there are many holy and learned Men have judg'd it unlawful, does prove it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be unlawful. And here it may deſerve Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the chief of thoſe you have inſtanc'd in, tho they are of Opinion that in ſome caſes it may be lawful to receive Profit for Loan (which caſes are very rarely obſerved, and particularly thoſe I ſhall hereafter mention under this ſame Head) tho I ſay they hold it in ſome Caſes lawful, yet they are very tender therein, and expreſs themſelves rather to this purpoſe, that they do not ſee the Unlawfulneſs of it, than aver confidently that it is unqueſtionably lawful. I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſhewed how little Incouragement any Man can have to practiſe Uſury, that ſhall impartially weigh what Bp <hi>Taylor</hi> hath written of it. As for Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> you produce him, <hi>Pag.</hi> 203. pleading, that if one Man delay and with-hold Payment beyond the time appointed, to the hindrance of the other,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:30287:14"/>the Party damnifi'd hereby may lawfully be conſider'd for it: and to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Pag.</hi> 219. pleading the Cauſe of the Lender thus; <q>Behold, I depended upon him, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to pay me at ſuch a day, that time is paſt and I can get nothing from him, he cares not tho I and my Family ſtarve for Hunger; therefore in ſuch Caſes Juſtice ought to remedy a Man. So then, if a Man be on this wiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, it is a clear caſe, he may take Intereſt again, and not for this be accuſed before either God or Men.</q> How little is this in favour of Uſury? Mr. <hi>J.</hi> whom you write againſt, allows the ſame, and calls it by the name of <hi>Intereſt,</hi> which he diſtinguiſhes from Uſury; and ſo do others as well as he, tho you like not the Diſtinction. Certainly a Man can take little Incouragement to practiſe Uſury from any thing that <hi>Calvin</hi> hath written: yea, if I had never read any other Perſon on this Subject, I ſhould reſolve rather to have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do with it. They who fled, or were baniſh'd in times of Perſecution, carrying Stocks of Money with them, and wanting Skill to imploy it in ſtrange places, did put it into the hands of others to trade with it, who gave them ſome Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance for the Uſe of their Money. This was a Caſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what extraordinary, and 'twas partly with a reſpect to thoſe Men, that ſome eminent Divines wrote ſo favourably of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, qualified with ſuch and ſuch Limitations as they have laid down. And ſo did <hi>Calvin,</hi> tho he ſays it were to be <hi>wiſhed that all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, yea the very name of it, were baniſh'd out of the World; and that he deſir'd nothing more than never to have any further occaſion offer'd him to meddle with that Subject;</hi> which I ſhall give you in his own Words, <hi>Optandum quidem eſſet omnes <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſuras, ipſum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> adeò nomen è Mundo jampridem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulâſſe, ut nihil magis exoptem quàm ut mihi neceſſitas non ſit Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentum iſtud deinceps attingere.</hi> And in his <hi>Harmony</hi> upon the <hi>Pentateuch, Certè minimè videtur licitum Filiis Dei, quod propha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Homines deteſtati ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt: Simus ubi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> &amp; ſemper
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:30287:14"/>exoſum &amp; infame fuiſſe faerneratorum nomen.</hi> And again, <hi>Fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus quidem exercere, cùm inter pudendos &amp; turpes quaeſ4us dux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erint prophani Scriptores, multò minus tolerabile eſt inter Filios Dei.</hi> And after he had ſpoken in defence of ſome kind of Uſury qualified according to his Rules and Reſtrictions, he adds theſe Words, <hi>Noto quidem meo patrocinio uſuras fovere, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> utinam nomen ipſum abolitum eſſet è Mundo.</hi> And in another place, after he had diſcourſed on this Subject, he concludes thus, <hi>Sed tenendum ſemper eſt, vix fieri poſſe, ut qui faenus acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit non gravet Fratrem ſuum: &amp; ideò optandum eſt nomen ipſum tam Faenoris quàm <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurae ſepultum eſſe &amp; deletum ex hominum memoriâ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> you have frequently quoted, and particularly his <hi>Practical Catechiſm:</hi> and yet he there ſays, that <hi>the buſineſs of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury is not ſo clearly ſtated in the New Teſtament, or in the Old, as that he can ſet ſtrict and certain Laws to a Man's Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from thence.</hi> He does indeed rather encline to think it lawful with this Caution among others, <hi>That he who lends, be (as far as morally he can be) ſure that he who pays him this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, be able to do it without eating out, or hurting himſelf, but that he makes greater Gain of it himſelf; and if either by miſ-adventure, or by his own neglects it be otherwiſe, 'tis the ſafeſt courſe to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear the Intereſt; and that in matters of this nature it is his Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to take the ſafeſt. Now,</hi> ſays he, <hi>if a Man think himſelf obliged ſo to do, 'twill make him the more circumſpect in exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Condition of the Perſon of whom he adventures to take <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, &amp;c.</hi> And afterwards, <hi>In all this,</hi> ſays he, <hi>you muſt not think that I am ſo poſitive as in other things I have been, &amp;c.</hi> And I find in the <hi>Life of Dr.</hi> Hammond, put forth by the Right Reverend Biſhop of <hi>Oxford,</hi> this obſerved concerning him, <hi>The taking of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, tho he judg'd it lawful, yet never ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd by Practice, but lent ſtill</hi> gratis <hi>both to Friends and Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</hi> Since then that Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> offers ſuch a Caution; and not he only, but <hi>Calvin</hi> too, who ſays further, that <hi>the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:30287:15"/>Borrower's Gain muſt be ſo much more at the leaſt as the Intereſt he pays,</hi> together with other Qualifications laid down by them and divers others; and particularly that of <hi>Zanchy</hi> and and <hi>Bucer,</hi> who held, <hi>That the Lender ought to ſhare in the loſs of the Principal, if it did happen to miſcarry in the Borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers hands,</hi> viz. that this muſt be their private purpoſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent tho it be not expreſt; and that fore-mention'd one of <hi>Ames, not to require all that a Man may by Law, but to keep within that which the Law permits;</hi> let it be conſider'd whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Man had not as good never meddle with it at all, as adventure upon that which the Principal of thoſe who have written in defence of it, preſcribe not only theſe above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd, but divers other <hi>Limitations</hi> and <hi>Cautions</hi> about, wherewith they apprehend it needful to qualify and tempes it to make it paſſable. And it may not be amiſs to conſider further, whether ſuch as plead theſe Mens Authorities, do obſerve the Cautions which are preſcribed by them. To all this I ſhall add theſe words of Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> in his <hi>Practical Caſes of Conſcience, All <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, which is an abſolute Contract for the meer Loan of Money, is unlawful, both by Law natural and poſitive, both divine and humane.</hi> And <hi>Grotius</hi> himſelf, whom you have quoted oftneſt of any other Author, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his Diſcourſe about it, makes this Profeſſion, <hi>Hâc de re acturus illud primùm praefabor, probare me eorum Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem, qui totum hoc luerandi genus ſublatum vellent è rebus hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manis, quando multa inde mala naſci manifeſtiſſimum eſt.</hi> I have thought it the more adviſeable to be thus large in my Reply to this fourth Argument of yours, becauſe there are divers I believe incouraged by the Authorities of ſuch emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Perſons, not only to allow themſelves freely in what they have written ſo nicely and tenderly of, but alſo to go beyond in ſeveral reſpects what theſe (and divers others who might be inſtanc'd in) have been careful to preſcribe in their reſpective Diſcourſes on this Subject.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:30287:15"/>
            <p> Your fifth Argument for Uſury, is the Neceſſity of it to the carrying on of Trade. But this, tho ſo ſtrongly urged, does not ſo plainly appear. Tradeſmen, if they did ſee it good, might take other meaſures, and yet find their Trade go on proſperouſly enough notwithſtanding. It does hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſo indeed (but I can ſee little reaſon for it) that they who write for the Lawfulneſs of Uſury, are counted the greater Friends to the trading part of the Nation: And this is one great Hinge you lay your Diſcourſe upon, as if Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry were the very Pillar and Baſis of Trade, without which it would fall to the ground. Did not the <hi>Romans</hi> flouriſh hundreds of Years before Uſury was practis'd among them (as one obſerves)? and the <hi>Jews</hi> did flouriſh in Wealth (none more) without any Toleration of Uſury. Tradeſmen have been ſo far concerned this way, that they do not generally deſire to hear any thing ſpoken againſt it: they have receiv'd conſiderable Increaſe by this way of dealing, and this darling Notion of the Neceſſity of it to Trade, is that they are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to take ſome Satisfaction from; tho there are ſome Tradeſmen on the other hand had better never have known what Uſury meant. But there is no great need of diſputing this one way or other, <hi>Whether <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury be a furtherance to Trade or no.</hi> If God's Word condemn it, 'tis no Man's Intereſt to practiſe it, and a weak Argument to ſay that Trade is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantag'd thereby: if God's Word do not condemn it, then let it be freely practis'd to all intents and purpoſes for which it can be render'd ſerviceable. And that muſt be the iſſue of this Diſpute, and not whether Trading be better'd by it or no. Only I wiſh it without any prejudice and imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally conſider'd, whether they who are not ſatisfied in the lawfulneſs of Uſury, may not be (whatever can evidently appear to the contrary) as great Friends to Trade, as the chiefeſt of thoſe who have written for the lawfulneſs of it. I ſhall conclude my Anſwer to this Argument with the words
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:30287:16"/>of that great and known Caſuiſt, Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> in his Sermon on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.24. <q>It were not poſſible <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurers</hi> ſhould be ſo bitterly inveighed againſt by ſober <hi>Heathen Writers,</hi> ſo ſeverely cenſured by the <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Canon</hi> Laws, ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formly condemned by godly <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Councils,</hi> ſo univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally hated by all Men of all ſorts, and in all Ages and Countries, as Hiſtories and Experience manifeſt they ever have been and are, if their Practice and Calling had been any way profitable, and not indeed every way hurtful and incommodious, both to private Men and publick Societies.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Your ſixth Argument is, That it is but doing as you would be done by. And yet you grant, <hi>Pag.</hi> 98. That he who lends to another, if he were to borrow himſelf, <hi>would not be willing by an abſolute and free-will</hi> to pay Intereſt; for, ſay you, <hi>If any would ſo far be-friend the Borrower, as to lend him</hi> gratis, <hi>this is of the two more eligible,</hi> for which you produce, <hi>Quis niſi mentis inops,</hi> &amp;c. But this in my Apprehenſion does not well agree with that Argument you are now treating of; and I ſhould think whatever may be ſaid of others, yet at leaſt ſuch as are of your Opinion in this matter, will do well to lend freely what they lend, becauſe they would like it well to have others lend freely to them. But the meaning of that great Law, <hi>Whatever we would that others ſhould do unto us, we are to do the ſame unto them,</hi> muſt be underſtood in ſuch caſes wherein we are rightly inform'd, (and ſo the doubt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ſtill in a great meaſure unſatisfied) otherwiſe I can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance wherein a Man will do very ill in doing to another what yet he may be too well contented another ſhould do to him. Beſides, Partiality may make me think that very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, when I am on the lending hand, which would not ſeem ſo to me if I were to borrow: and it ſeems you by your good will would have others lend you freely, in caſe they could perſwade themſelves to be ſo kind.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:30287:16"/>
            <p> Your ſeventh Argument is, That there are divers caſes wherein 'tis hard to make it appear that Uſury is more biting than other ways of dealing, that are approv'd of by thoſe who condemn Uſury. You give divers Inſtances to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe which are very proper and pertinent; but there is one of the Inſtances you have produced that I do not ſee any Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency in; which is, of a Man that borrows upon Uſe a Sum of Money to purchaſe an Eſtate of Land, on which there is Timber enough to inable this Purchaſer to pay back the whole Sum again; for here the Price paid for the Land is not a valuable Conſideration; and this kind of arguing would ſerve to juſtify the receiving more for the Loan of Money (and yet the Borrower not be bitten) than I believe the moſt biting and oppreſſive Uſurer in the World did ever receive. 'Tis fit every Man that purchaſes Land, ſhould pay a Price in ſome good meaſure anſwerable to the real value of the Land, and of the Timber too that is upon it: and if ſo, he that borrows Money upon Uſe to purchaſe Land, may in a ſhort time ſee cauſe to repent his Bargain. But there are Caſes, I confeſs, in which 'tis difficult to find out how Uſury ſhould be more biting then ſome other ways of dealing that are allowed of on all hands; with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to which Caſes, I ſhall offer theſe two things to your Conſideration. Firſt, Whether the like caſes might not have been pleaded by a Jew that ſhould have practis'd Uſury with his Brethren? And yet the chief of thoſe Authors you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in favour of it now, do hold that it was unlawful to the Jews. Secondly, Whether the Wit of Man may not find out divers ſubtil Arguments, and propound Caſes very ſpecious and plauſible in defence of that, which yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is not juſtifiable in it ſelf? Yea, in Mathematical Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences (tho in them there be the plaineſt Demonſtration) are Arguments produced <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> which are to our Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions undeniable on both ſides. But if God's Law
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:30287:17"/>forbid it (which is that I regard more than all Arguments from other Topicks) to what purpoſe is it for us to urge, that there are Caſes may be thought on, wherein we are not able to ſee the Iniquity of it? Neither can you eaſily ſee wherein 'tis inconſiſtent with Equity (as I have intimated before) to take Uſe of a poor Man for Loan of Money, any more than to take Rent for his Houſe; and yet you do not ſeem to like that your ſelf, to take Uſe of a poor Man. We can ſee but a little way, and are not to make our Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions a meaſure for Divine Laws. We ſhall be guilty of aſſuming too much to our own weak and ſhallow Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, if we would endeavour to bring all things to their Standard. <hi>Man's Wit is ſet on work</hi> (ſays a learned and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Writer) <hi>to ſpin out fine and ſubtil Caſes of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no wrong ſhall appear. 'Tis an eaſy matter to caſt a Stone into a Pool, which ſeven wiſe Men will hardly get out: and one ſuch Caſe will beget many Caſes like unto it ſelf, for the Wit of Man will work like a Mole to get into the Earth.</hi> To which I ſhall ſubjoyn the Opinion of a worthy Perſon I lately diſcourſed with on this Subject, <q>That God hath given this Law againſt Uſury on purpoſe to try Mens Obedience: he allows them other ways of dealing as advantagious as Uſury, but this way, he ſays, they ſhall not make uſe of; and does it to try their Obedience, and to ſee whether they will be govern'd by him therein or no.</q>
            </p>
            <p>What you urge in behalf of Widows and Orphans, which I know is generally pleaded, does not (that I can ſee) ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify very much to the deciding of this Controverſy. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs God had a tender regard to them, beyond what the moſt compaſſionate Men in the World can have, put them alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and we find does take a particular care of them; but yet he has no where excepted them as to this matter. And to what purpoſe is it for us to interpoſe where God's Word is ſilent? The greater care God hath himſelf been
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:30287:17"/>pleaſed to expreſs concerning them is an Argument to truſt God the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to depend the more on his Providence. And I believe it may puzzle any Man to give any ſatisfactory Reaſon to the contrary, but that Widows and Orphans may be as well provided for now without Uſury, as they were among the Jews, or other Nations where Uſury hath been ſtrictly prohibited. The Queſtion is, <hi>Whether <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury be forbidden us or no, by God's Law?</hi> If it be not, then 'tis lawful for others, as well as Orphans and Widows: if it be, 'tis as unlawful for them as others, there being no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception at all in God's Word concerning them, with reference to this matter.</p>
            <p>And thus you may poſſibly ſee your Arguments are not altogether ſo ſtrong as I believe you took them to be, when you ſpeake ſo ſlightly of what has been urged to the contrary by Bp <hi>Jewel, Pag.</hi> 113. <q>But what ſpeak I (ſaith Bp <hi>Jewel</hi>) of the ancient Fathers? there was never any Religion, nor Sect, nor State, nor Degree, nor Profeſſion of Men, but they have miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked it.</q> You reply, <hi>And that deſervedly too, if this be meant of oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, otherwiſe none is bound to believe him, and 'tis hard to prove the truth of it.</hi> Somewhat like to this is the Reply you give to Biſhop <hi>Hall. Nature teacheth,</hi> ſays Biſhop <hi>Hall, that Metals are not capable of Superfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi> You reply, <q>If they be capable of Fetation, it is enough; and when the Barrenneſs of Metals is pleaded, I may ſafely think it is not meant of Metals in the Mine, for there they receive a natural Increaſe, at leaſt by Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</q> So where <hi>Ainſworth</hi> cites <hi>Maimonides,</hi> the learned <hi>Rabbi,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing with ſome Strictneſs againſt Uſury, p. 218. you comment thus upon him, <hi>Strange it is that Eagles ſhould thus catch Flies, and great Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies learnedly diſcourſe of Trifles.</hi> And yet I find the learned <hi>Ames,</hi> who I think of all Men has pleaded the Cauſe of Uſury beſt, diſcourſing as criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, or nicely (if you will call it ſo) concerning <hi>Simony,</hi> where he ſayes, <hi>Hinc munus Simoniacum non ineptè dividitur in munus à manu, munus à linguâ, &amp; munus ab obſequio, &amp;c.</hi> To which I ſhall refer you.</p>
            <p>The next thing I ſhall take notice of, is the Expoſition you give of what we read in <hi>Nehem.</hi> 5. concerning Uſury, where you ſay, that it ſeems to you not an improbable Conjecture that the hundredth part of the Money, &amp;c. <hi>v.</hi> 11. is not to be underſtood of Uſury, but that proportion which the Officers and Rulers did for their Service exact from the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. If you make the beſt of this, 'tis but a Conjecture: and I conceive, 'twould be almoſt endleſs to ſhew how different 'tis from the main ſtream and current of Expoſitors. I ſhall only mention two, which you have had recourſe to your ſelf, and therefore may weigh more with you than others. The firſt is <hi>Diodat,</hi> who ſays, <hi>The hundreth part was a Tax of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:30287:18"/>at one in the hundred by the Month.</hi> The other is the <hi>Annotations,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly call'd the <hi>Aſſemblies,</hi> in which ſome parts of the Scripture are excellently well handled, and others as meanly, but I think 'twas Dr. <hi>Gouge</hi> that was appointed to be the Commentator on this Book of <hi>Nehemiah;</hi> and he was a very worthy Expoſitor, as appears by his ſolid and accurate Expoſition on the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> who ſays on this Text, <q>The meaning is, that they ſhould reſtore all that they had taken upon Uſe, for they uſed to take the hundredth part of what they lent every Month. That which they had thus received for Intereſt, they were to reſtore again, and that in kind, whether it were Money, or any other Commodity; for theſe four, Money, Corn, Wine, Oil, are put for all manner of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities that were given for Intereſt.</q> Your arguing from <hi>ver.</hi> 10. is leſs plauſible than your former Conjecture. What if he meant not that he and his Brethren in Government might exact <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> of the People, (which 'tis not likely he did intend) was it not proper enough for him however to plead with them thus, <q>If I, and my Brethren in Command with me, do not exact that Tribute and Cuſtom that is due to us for the Support and Maintenance of the Government, much more ſhould you forbear exacting ſuch Uſury as you do require?</q> And tho this caſe were extraordinary (which is another Anſwer you give) 'twill not follow that thoſe Uſurers might exact in like manner at other times. This Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry might be oppreſſive at all times, tho at this time it was the more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous by reaſon of the preſent Straits the People were under.</p>
            <p>Thers is another thing you propoſe to Conſideration, <hi>Pag.</hi> 86. which you find in a learned Writer, whoſe Words you render into <hi>Engliſh</hi> thus: <q>Hitherto may be referred, that it is very probable from that Parable of the Talents, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.27. not only that there was ſome Uſury of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney-Changers in common uſe amongſt the Jews, but alſo that it was not diſallowed of our Lord: becauſe under that Similitude he requires a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Office without the leaſt hint of any Diſallowance, the which he was wont to uſe in other Parables, which illuſtrated Duty from diſallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Cuſtoms, as <hi>Luke</hi> 16.8.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Argument for Uſury from what our Saviour ſays in that place, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.27. <hi>Thou oughteſt therefore to have put my Money to the Exchangers, and then at my coming I ſhould have received mine own with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury;</hi> has been thought to be more properly confuted than confirm'd by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring of this with that other Text, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.8. <hi>And the Lord commended the unjuſt Steward, becauſe he had done wiſely: for the Children of this World are in their Generation wiſer than the Children of Light;</hi> the unjuſt Steward
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:30287:18"/>being rather commended in this Text than condemn'd. But if the unjuſt Steward's Practice be here brought in with an hint of Diſallowance, there is another Inſtance of the like nature where there is not the leaſt hint of any Diſallowance at all; and that is, where our Saviour compares his coming, <hi>to a Thief in the Night.</hi> Whether <hi>Dancing,</hi> and ſuch kind of <hi>Races</hi> as were uſed in the Olympick Games, be lawful Exerciſes or no, I ſhall not here enter into any diſpute about: but, according to this way of arguing, the Diſputes that have been with reference to either of them, may ſoon be reſolv'd, for there is not the leaſt hint of any Diſallowance where mention is made of them in Scripture, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.17. <hi>We have piped unto you, and ye have not danced:</hi> and 1 Cor 9.24. <hi>They that run in a Race. run all, but one receiveth the Prize.</hi> We muſt not ſtrain Similitudes to make every Particular agree, as a Commentator obſerves on that place of St. <hi>Luke.</hi> In ſuch Parabolical Diſcourſes the main drift of them is what we are to attend unto; and not apprehend that every thing mention'd in them, without a particular Expreſſion of Diſallowance, is approv'd of. As for the <hi>Money-Changers,</hi> I do not deny but they were Uſurers: that ſeems plain enough from the Text; and there is an ingenious Writer ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves this to be the conſtant Signification of the word <hi>Trapezitae,</hi> or <hi>Table<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> in prophane Authors: but he makes his Obſervation to a different purpoſe, and urges our Saviour's calling them a Company of <hi>Thieves,</hi> as an Argument againſt Uſury, on <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.12, 13. <q>If we look well, ſays he, into our Saviour's Behaviour in this Act, we ſhall find that as by his overthrowing their Tables, and thruſting them out, he chaſtized their Prophaneneſs; ſo by his verbal Reproof, he taxes their very Imployment, calling them a Company of Thieves, <hi>Ye have made it a Den of Thieves.</hi> This <hi>[Ye]</hi> cannot be meant of the Buyers and Sellers: Buying and Selling is a very warantable thing, eſpecially ſure when it relates to the Service of God, as theirs did. Beſides, Chriſt gave them their Leſſon by themſelves, as St. <hi>John</hi> tells us, <hi>John</hi> 2.16. <hi>Make not my Fathers Houſe an Houſe of Merchandiſe.</hi> It remains then that the <hi>[Ye]</hi> muſt be directed to the Uſurers, whom he ranks among Thieves. And this Writer concludes this Obſervation thus, <hi>If any body has a Mind to ſalve the matter, and ſay, Perhaps they were not honeſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurers, I am of the ſame Mind, and ſo at laſt we are unawares agreed.</hi>
               </q> You confeſs you ſee not the Cogency of the Argument you have quoted; and I will grant you that I ſee not the Cogency of this; and ſo let one go againſt the other.</p>
            <p>But I am as little ſatisfied in your own way of reaſoning, <hi>Pag.</hi> 160. where you argue thus; <q>'Tis beyond diſpute that there is too much Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:30287:19"/>to be found in the Land; but whether moderate Gain for Loan be ſuch, he knows is in diſpute between learned, pious, and good Men; and I think a Man may hold either ſide of the Queſtion, and his Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be little concern'd in it: only I ſhall ſay, the practice thereof on the one hand is of great Conſequence to the Nation we live in, as well as to the Eſtates of many ſingle Perſons; and the peremptory condemning of all that uſe it, is of dangerous Conſequence on the other hand, upon Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals that it be falſe.</q> You plead elſewhere, <hi>That things may be weighed on both ſides with equal Ballances.</hi> Now pray conſider whether this matter you have now in <hi>Deliberation,</hi> be not to be ballanced more equally thus; <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all covenanted Gain for Loan be ſinful, is in diſpute between learned, pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and good Men: therefore as the peremptory condemning of it is of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Conſequence, on the one hand, upon ſuppoſal that it be lawful; ſo the general practice of it is of dangerous Conſequence on the other hand, upon ſuppoſal that it be ſinful.</hi> Eſpecially ſince you do elſewhere, ſc. <hi>Pag.</hi> 241. implicitely acknowledg it <hi>not clearly ſtated in the Word, and that which continues diſputable between good and learned Men.</hi> Which gives me occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to deſire there might be ſome more ſatisfactory Anſwer given to this Query of your own, mention'd, <hi>Pag.</hi> 1.128. <hi>Is it not moſt adviſeable, where there are two ways, the one doubtful and dangerous, the other not, to chuſe the ſafeſt?</hi> I ſay, I could heartily wiſh this Query might be more ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factorily anſwer'd by ſome Perſon or other with reference to this preſent Subject. <hi>'Tis very doubtful,</hi> ſays Mr. <hi>Vines</hi> (as you quote him, <hi>Pag.</hi> 2.) <hi>whether <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury be a Sin or no.</hi> You ſay, <hi>Pag.</hi> 160. <hi>'Tis in diſpute between learned, pious, and good Men,</hi> and do implicitely confeſs, <hi>Pag.</hi> 241. <hi>That it is not clearly ſtated in the Word of God:</hi> 'tis condemned by <hi>General Councils,</hi> by the <hi>Greek and Latin Fathers,</hi> by the <hi>Canon and the Civil Law:</hi> 'tis condemn'd both by the <hi>Eſtabliſh'd Doctrine of the Church of England</hi> in the Book of Homilies, and by the late <hi>Aſſembly of Divines</hi> in their <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> as alſo in the <hi>Engliſh Annotations,</hi> publiſh'd by ſome Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of that Aſſembly thereunto appointed. Yea, and <hi>Rivet</hi> himſelf (who hath ſo often anſwer'd for you) does yet confeſs that <hi>all the Canoniſts and Schoolmen on this Queſtion as alſo divers learned and orthodox Men who follow them</hi> (particularly he inſtanceth in Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> Dr. <hi>Wilſon,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi>) <hi>do condemn all kind of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury whatſoever.</hi> I ſay then, conſidering all this, does not he take the ſafeſt courſe, who imploys his Money ſome ſuch way (whereof there is ſufficient choice and variety) as is concluded on all hands to be lawful and warrantable? He who hath a Portion leſt him in Money, is not neceſſitated (as your Diſcourſe ſeems
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:30287:19"/>to imply) to one of theſe two, either to lend it out upon Uſe, or to lend it freely: there are many other ways for him to diſpoſe of it to very good and reaſonable Advantage; whereas ſuch as allow themſelves in this practice of Uſury, are greatly concern'd to ſee it clearly made out, that this <hi>Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of it in God's Word</hi> does not concern them; there being, ſo long as this remains doubtful, ſo great a Danger and Adventure on the one hand, as is ſufficient to weigh down the moſt plauſible Conjectures that can be offer'd on the other. The Teſtimonies you produce in favour of Uſury, are of ſuch Men for the moſt part, as have written very tenderly of it; tho they are inclin'd to believe that it may be lawful, yet 'tis only in <hi>ſome Caſes,</hi> and with certain <hi>Cautions</hi> and <hi>Limitations:</hi> but on the other hand, how many are there that do hold it very diſputable and doubtful, tho they will not peremptorily conclude it to be ſinful; and others that do judg it ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely ſinful? Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> is generally acknowledg'd one of the moſt able, accurate and judicious Writers that have ever written in matters of Conſcience; and he in his Sermon on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.24. after he ſays, that <hi>moſt of the Learned have concluded <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury ſimply unlawful,</hi> has theſe words, <q>I ſhould be very tender to condemn any thing as ſimply unlawful, which any, even imaginary Conjuncture of Circumſtances would render law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; and would chuſe rather by an over-liberal Charity to cover a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Sins, than by a too ſuperſtitious Reſtraint make one. Yet the Texts of Scripture are ſo expreſs, and the Grounds of Reaſon ſo ſtrong againſt all Uſury, that when I weigh theſe on the one ſide, and on the other ſide, how nothing all that is which I ever yet ſaw or heard al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to the contrary, I cannot find in my ſelf Charity enough to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve any kind of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> with what Cautions or Circumſtances ſoever qualified, from being a Sin.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As for theſe many Scruples, you ſay, that Mr. <hi>J.</hi> has occaſion'd by his Doctrine in tender Conſciences, I have theſe three Conſiderations to offer in Reply thereunto.</p>
            <p>Firſt; That 'tis not only Mr. <hi>J</hi>'s Doctrine, but that which is delivered by ſo many and ſo able Writers, as may ſufficiently warrant a Man's chuſing rather to imploy his Money ſome other way. <hi>In dubiis tutior pars eligenda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly; Tho a Man ought to watch againſt Scrupuloſity, as a very troubleſome vexatious Diſtemper, which may alſo prove a great Snare to him, and uſe his beſt Endeavours in all matters that concern him to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form his Conſcience aright; yet of the two Extreams, a Man is leſs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger'd by this. To which purpoſe our late able, learned, religious <hi>Judg
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:30287:20"/>Hales</hi> has expreſt himſelf thus, in that excellent Diſcourſe of his, call'd <hi>The great Audit,</hi> 
               <q>I have more trembled under the Fear of a ſeared than a ſcrupulous Conſcience; becauſe I always counted the latter, tho more troubleſome, yet more ſafe. I have choſen rather to forbear that which ſeemed but indifferent, leſt there ſhould be ſome thing in it that might be unlawful; and would rather gratify my Conſcience with being too ſcrupulous, then flat it by being too adventurous. I have ſtill choſen ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to forbear what might be probably lawful, than to do that which might be poſſibly unlawful; becauſe I could not err in the former, I might in the latter. If things were diſputable whether they might be done, I rather choſe to forbear, becauſe the Lawfulneſs of my Forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance was unqueſtionable.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly; They who are incourag'd to practiſe Uſury by ſuch Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as you have pleaded in defence thereof, if ever they come after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to doubt of it, will find greater Perplexity than thoſe who ſcruple at it firſt of all (if it be a Scruple) and for that Reaſon forbear it alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> I know allows of ſome kind of Uſury, and you have urged his Authority for it among others: But what he writes in reference to any doubtful way of Uſury, I ſhall here apply to Uſury in general, which I think may without any breach of Modeſty or Charity be ſaid to be doubtful, and for my part, I will not ſay 'tis ſinful; in his <hi>Directions</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Reſtitution and Satisfaction, where his ſecond Direction is this, <q>Do nothing that is doubtful if you can avoid it, leſt it ſhould put you upon the trouble of Reſtitution: As in caſe of any doubtful way of Uſury or other Gain, conſider that if it ſhould hereafter appear to you to be unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and ſo you be obliged to Reſtitution (tho you thought it lawful at the taking of it) what a Snare then would you be in when all that Uſe muſt be repayed?</q> I think ſuch as Mr. <hi>J.</hi> are not the only Perſons who may be ſaid to be the Cauſes of Perplexities about this matter to Mens Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; but ſuch alſo as do incourage them to this way of dealing, which they are not able clearly to juſtify. Men are generally deſirous of Gain, and will be nibbling even at hazardous and doubtful ways of compaſſing it; ready in the firſt place to catch at any Arguments that may ſerve in ſome ſort to countenance the Practice of what they have a Mind to: And then ſome time afterwards, upon one occaſion or other, the Conſciences of ſome of them ſmite them for it, and will not ſuffer them quietly to keep what they have gotten this way. And they who were ſatisfy'd before by the leaſt Argument, are not now quieted with all the Reaſons and Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that are offer'd them to juſtify what they have done, but do wiſh
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:30287:20"/>they had never been ſo imbolden'd to it by thoſe whoſe Conduct they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly thought they might very ſafely follow. I am very ſenſible how ill an Office it is to create any unneceſſary Perplexities to the Conſciences of Men; and that there is ſcarce any thing of a more perplexing nature, than the matter of Reſtitution in doubtful Cafes, to ſuch as cannot tell how to quiet themſelves as they ought to do by reaſon of the Predominancy of their Fears. For my own part, I dare not ſay that Uſury is ſinful, and that what hath been gotten that way ought in good Conſcience to be reſtor'd. I ſhould be very loth, in ſo doubtful a Caſe, to charge any Perſon with an Obligation of Reſtitution; for notwithſtanding all that I have ſaid in Anſwer to your Arguments, I have ſeen ſo much that hath been pleaded in defence of the Lawfulneſs of Uſury, as would make me very loth to put any Man upon reſtoring what he hath receiv'd this way. 'Tis a known Maxim, <hi>Melior eſt conditio poſſidentis;</hi> and I ſee no ſufficient Reaſon to move any Perſon to Reſtitution in this caſe, tho he be not altogether ſo well ſatisfy'd in what he has as he would deſire, if it do not appear to him to have been unlawful Gain. But this is the <hi>Iſſue</hi> I am willing to bring this Diſpute unto, whether in reference <hi>to the time to come</hi> (for I would rather look forward in ſuch uncertain and doubtful matters than back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward) I ſay, whether for the future any Man that conſiders what hath been before-mention'd, will not act more adviſedly in having nothing to do with this way of dealing. And the rather, becauſe tho he boggle not at it now, yet his Conſcience may hereafter ſit more uneaſie than he thinks of at preſent, if he do adventure on it upon ſuch uncertain Reſolutions, as thoſe are which I have above taken notice of. One ſays Uſury was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden <hi>only to the Poor.</hi> Another ſays, 'twas forbidden to the Poor and Rich that were <hi>Jews,</hi> but <hi>only to the Jews</hi> among themſelves. A third ſays, 'twas not all kind of Uſury that was forbidden to any, but <hi>only biting <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> And the Reſolutions are as uncertain how to underſtand when it is biting, and when it is not biting. One ſays, 'tis not biting if it do not exceed what the Law of the Land allows; and yet the Law it ſelf ſays, that nothing therein contained ſhall be conſtrued or expounded to allow of the practice of Uſury in point of Religion or Conſcience. Another ſays, 'tis the ſafeſt courſe for him that puts out his Money, not to require all that he may by Law, but to keep within that which the Law permits. A third ſays, He that lends his Money, ſhould be (as far as morally he can be) ſure that he who pays him this Uſe, be able to do it without eating out, or hurting himſelf, but that he makes greater gain of it himſelf: and if either by miſadventure, or by his own neglect, it be
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:30287:21"/>otherwiſe, 'tis the ſafeſt courſe to forbear the Intereſt, and that in matters of this nature it is his duty to take the ſafeſt. A fourth ſays, The Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower's Gain muſt be ſo much more at leaſt as the Intereſt he pays. A fifth ſays, The Lender muſt purpoſe and intend privately with himſelf to ſhare in the loſs of the Principal, if it happen to miſcarry in the Borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers hands. We ſee, they who had a mind to ſay ſomething in deſence of ſome kind of Uſury, have made ſuch Parings and Mincings of it, that a Man will do better, I ſhould think, in all reſpects to let it alone altogether. And if any Perſon will undertake to make it appear that this is not a Man's wiſeſt way, and that he ſhall not by ſo doing conſult the Eaſe and Quiet of his Conſcience beſt; I ſhall be very glad to ſee any thing more ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally pleaded by him, than what I have offer'd; for I wiſh nothing more in this matter than the clear Determination of it, which way ſoever it ſhall fall.</p>
            <p>And now, Sir, I think it high time to draw to a Concluſion. The like Conſideration that inclin'd you to animadvert with ſo much Freedom on the Writings of others, may excuſe me to you for making theſe Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on your own. I am altogether an Enemy to that Cenſoriouſneſs you write againſt, being willing to joyn heartily with you therein; and deſire, in all humble and deep Senſe of my own weak and ſlender Apprehenſions, to eſteem and honour all good People whatſoever, whether they be of the ſame Perſwaſion with my ſelf or no, either in this or any other matter. For which Reaſon I may with the greater Aſſurance deſire of you the like meaſure again, who am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
